Oh, God!
老天
It's a little early, isn't it?
现在做这个有点太早了吧
Go back to sleep. I don't need you awake for this.
继续睡吧  我不需要你醒着才能做
Honey, it's Christmas Eve.
亲爱的  今天是平安夜
Are you gonna spend all day on that thing?
你要一整天都耗在那玩意儿上吗
I made a promise.
我发过誓了
Yes!
没错
Last Christmas, Phil got an elliptical machine
去年圣诞节  菲尔买了一台椭圆健身机
and vowed to walk the equivalent
还发誓要在一年内走完
of our house to Canada in one year.
相当于从我们家到加拿大的公里数
This body doesn't just happen, ladies.
我这身材可不是说有就有的  女士们
If he didn't make it,
如果他做不到
no machine in the bedroom.
卧室里不准再放任何机器
Except for this machine in the bedroom, ladies.
除了我这台机器  女士们
Who are these ladies?
这些女士们到底是谁
Oh, Phil, give it up.
菲尔  放弃吧
Oh, you would love that, wouldn't you?
那你一定乐开花了吧
Just when I'm so close to the Canadian border,
我就快到达加拿大边境了
I can smell the bacon
都能闻到培根的香味
and the reasonably priced medications.
还有定价合理的药品了
Mom, this came for you from nana.
老妈  这是外婆寄给你的
I don't know why she bothers to wrap it every year.
不知道为什么她每年都要费劲包装一下
It's always the same thing -- slippers.
内容永远不变  拖鞋
You never know. She might surprise you this year.
谁知道呢  说不定她今年会给你个惊喜
Would you care to take a visit
你有没有兴趣
to the museum of maternal indifference?
逛逛冷漠母亲博物馆
Watch it!
小心点
Oh, careful!
小心
You guys are really moving her downstairs right now?
非要现在就搬到楼下吗
Aren't you gonna be late for work?
上班不会迟到吗
They're not gonna fire an elf on Christmas Eve.
他们不会在圣诞前夕开除精灵的
Ugh, I thought this would be lighter without my shoes on it.
我以为不放鞋子  这柜子能轻点呢
You know, once you set up your room,
等你整理好房间
you could put books on this.
可以放些书上去
Books...on a shoe shelf.
鞋架上放书
Right.
想什么呢
- You're not gonna jump on that? - I'm just too happy!
-你不反驳一下吗  -我太开心了
After today,
今天过后
there'll be no more clothes thrown everywhere,
我房间里就不会再有人到处乱扔衣服
no more hour-long phone calls
不会有人打好几个小时的电话
where all she says is "No way."
全程只会说"不可能"
I think it's a little sad
你们决定今天分开住
that you guys are doing this today.
我觉得有点悲伤啊
I remember when you used to get
我记得你们以前总是
into the same bed on Christmas Eve
在平安夜睡同一张床
and talk about all the presents you were gonna get.
然后一起聊你们将得到的礼物
It's a perfect day for it!
今天搬再合适不过了
When I wake up in my own room tomorrow,
等我明天在我自己的房间醒来
I'm going to be giving thanks for my independence.
我会感谢我获得独立
And isn't that what Christmas is all about?
那不正是圣诞节的意义所在吗
Seriously? Nothing?
真的吗  什么都不说吗
m 20 0 l 209 0 b 218 0 229 11 229 20 l 229 209 b 229 218 218 228 209 228 l 20 228 b 11 228 0 218 0 209 l 0 20 b 0 11 11 0 20 0
本字幕由人人影视字幕组翻译 禁止用作任何商业盈利行为
m 325 0 l 355 0 l 332 47 l 354 47 l 399 136 l 369 136 l 328 53 l 288 136 l 257 136 l 325 0 m 467 0 l 497 0 l 474 47 l 496 47 l 541 136 l 511 136 l 470 53 l 430 136 l 399 136 l 467 0 m 545 1 l 583 1 l 583 14 l 568 14 l 568 19 l 583 19 l 583 30 l 568 30 l 568 34 l 599 34 l 599 30 l 583 30 l 583 19 l 599 19 l 599 14 l 583 14 l 583 1 l 611 1 b 616 1 622 6 622 10 l 622 36 l 652 0 l 678 0 l 644 41 l 622 41 l 622 47 l 596 47 l 597 54 l 625 54 l 625 68 l 541 68 l 541 54 l 572 54 l 571 47 l 545 47 l 545 1 m 583 72 l 583 85 l 569 85 l 569 90 l 598 90 l 598 85 l 583 85 l 583 72 l 611 72 b 615 72 621 78 621 82 l 653 44 l 678 44 l 644 86 l 621 86 l 621 103 l 597 103 l 597 136 l 570 136 l 564 126 l 562 136 l 542 136 l 548 107 l 568 107 l 565 121 l 571 121 l 571 103 l 547 103 l 547 72 l 583 72 m 600 107 l 620 107 l 624 124 l 653 89 l 679 89 l 642 136 l 615 136 l 618 132 l 606 132 l 600 107 m 689 0 l 716 0 l 721 15 l 732 15 l 732 30 l 718 56 l 731 56 l 735 100 l 721 100 l 717 59 l 714 64 l 714 136 l 693 136 l 693 79 l 676 79 l 707 30 l 679 30 l 679 15 l 694 15 l 689 0 m 738 0 l 804 0 b 807 0 813 6 813 9 l 813 87 l 794 87 l 794 14 l 756 14 l 756 87 l 763 77 l 763 21 l 787 21 l 787 91 l 798 91 l 798 120 l 820 120 l 812 136 l 778 136 l 778 90 l 748 136 l 723 136 l 756 87 l 738 87 l 738 0 m 257 151 l 275 151 l 297 182 l 319 151 l 337 151 l 304 197 l 304 227 l 290 227 l 290 197 l 257 151 m 337 151 l 355 151 l 377 182 l 399 151 l 417 151 l 384 197 l 384 227 l 370 227 l 370 197 l 337 151 m 425 192 l 447 192 b 445 181 427 181 425 192 l 410 192 b 414 162 458 162 462 192 l 462 206 l 425 206 b 425 210 429 212 433 213 l 462 213 l 462 227 l 433 227 b 412 227 408 203 410 192 m 462 151 l 532 151 l 532 165 l 504 165 l 504 227 l 489 227 l 489 165 l 462 165 l 462 151 m 580 172 l 580 186 l 549 186 b 543 186 543 192 549 192 l 565 192 b 589 192 589 227 565 227 l 532 227 l 532 213 l 565 213 b 570 213 570 206 565 206 l 549 206 b 524 206 524 172 549 172 l 580 172 m 592 213 l 606 213 l 606 227 l 592 227 l 592 213 m 639 172 l 665 172 l 665 186 l 639 186 b 623 186 623 213 639 213 l 665 213 l 665 227 l 639 227 b 603 227 603 172 639 172 m 700 184 b 722 184 722 215 700 215 l 700 229 b 740 229 740 170 700 170 b 660 170 660 229 700 229 l 700 215 b 680 215 680 184 700 184 m 737 172 l 782 172 b 803 172 813 177 813 198 l 813 228 l 799 228 l 799 198 b 799 186 793 187 782 187 l 782 228 l 768 228 l 768 187 l 752 187 l 752 228 l 737 228 l 737 172
■
This is your great-grandmother's recipe.
这是你曾祖母的菜谱
If she could see you now...
如果她现在能看到你
...she would die again, because you're doing it wrong!
她会死第二次的  因为你弄错了
My mother has been here all week.
我母亲来这里一星期了
I love her very much, but you know what they say --
我非常爱她  但你也知道常言说
house guests start to stink after three days,
客人待三天就开始招人烦[发臭]了
like dead bodies.
就跟尸体一样
What the hell is that?
那是什么玩意儿
A fiber-optic tree.
光纤圣诞树
It's way better for the environment than a real one.
这比用真正的树对环境有利
Not if the environment is my living room.
但对我家客厅这个环境就不利
Look, I admit, it takes some getting used to,
我承认  这得适应一段时间
but so did greek yogurt.
但就像希腊酸奶一样
Now I can't even remember how the old stuff tastes.
我现在都记不清原来的酸奶是什么味道了
Why do we keep changing things that don't need changing?
人们为什么总是改变不需要改变的东西
Christmas is real trees and eggnog,
过圣诞节就得有真正的圣诞树  蛋酒
Perry Como and bing on the hi-fi.
佩里・科莫还有高保真音响突然的巨响
Now you're just making up words.
你这是在瞎掰
I'm drawing a line in the sand.
我这是在表明立场
We're gonna get a real tree,
我们马上去找一棵真正的树
and we're gonna cut it down like I did when I was a kid.
然后像我小时候那样砍倒它
Follow me.
跟我来
Hi, dad.
老爸
Can't talk. Saving Christmas.
没空聊天  我在拯救圣诞节
Hi. Thank you again for coming.
再次感谢你能来
No problem. I love babysitting!
不客气  我超爱看孩子
Good! We're going to run some quick errands.
太好了  我们要去办点事儿
Wait, if you're taking Joe --
等等  如果你要带走乔
Hola, Claire!
你好啊  克莱尔
Around 4:00, she gets fussy for her bottle.
大概四点左右回来  她很挑剔她的水瓶
Lily, do you know why I'm able to relax
莉莉  你知道今天我为什么能
and read this paper today?
这么放松地看报纸吗
Because you don't have a job?
因为你没有工作吗
FYI, I am starting a new job in exactly t--
告诉你  再过几天我就要开始新工
No. We're not doing this again.
算了  我不再重复了
It's because I planned ahead.
是因为我提前计划好了
I finished my Christmas shopping weeks ago.
我几周前就完成了圣诞购物
It's important to keep busy.
保持紧张忙碌非常重要
I-it is perfectly normal to take some downti--
偶尔休息一下也非常正常
No. No!
不  算了
Okay.
好吧
I printed out the directions to Pepper's party.
我把胡娇的派对指南打印出来了
We're calling it "The 12 Gays of Christmas" now.
现在改名叫"十二圣诞基佬"了
Oh, just be thankful
我们说服他没用
we talked him out of "Feliz Navidude."
"快乐基男"已经要谢天谢地了
Okay, honey, finish your breakfast
好了  亲爱的  快吃完早饭
so we can go help our fellow man!
我们要去帮我们的同胞了
One hour at this charity event, max.
去慈善活动上参与一小时  最多
I can't eat.
我吃不了了
I'm too excited to get my Puppy Pound.
就要得到我的胖胖狗之家了  我好激动
I'm -- I'm sorry. Your what?
我  抱歉  你说你的什么
Puppy pounds have six puppies
胖胖狗之家里有六只小狗
with online profiles.
每只都有网络档案
Ask your parents before using the Internet.
上网前要寻求家长同意
Honey, you never mentioned a-a-a puppy pound.
亲爱的  你从没提过什么胖胖狗之家啊
- What is she talking about? - I-it's not on your list.
-她在说什么  -礼物单上没有这个
Yes, it is. "Puppy Pound."
有啊  在这儿  "胖胖狗之家"
Oh, no! She put a "P" backwards.
不是吧  她把"P"写反了
And, honey, there's a "u" in "Pound."
而且亲爱的  "Pound"里有字母"u"
- This says "Guppy Pond"! - Guppy Pond!
-这写的是"古比鱼池"  -古比鱼池
What is a Guppy Pond?
什么是古比鱼池
It's only the -- the coolest gift ever!
这是  有史以来最酷的礼物
I want a Puppy Pound.
我要胖胖狗之家
Um, honey, it's C--
亲爱的  今天是圣
Okay.
好了
I am not pointing fingers,
我不是要指责谁
but our daughter had
但我们女儿在清单上
exactly one thing on her list,
明明白白列出了一样东西
and someone didn't get it,
但某人却没有买到
so someone needs to go to the mall.
所以某人现在得去商场
You're pointing fingers.
你在"指"责我
No. It's still a "1."
不  这还是个"1"
It just fell asleep on the job.
只不过它偷懒睡着了
Ellipticaler's log, 12/24.
健身日志  12月24日
10 miles from Canadian border.
距离加拿大边界还有10英里
Spirits -- high. Stamina -- strong.
情绪高涨  精力充沛
Must get another application of thigh lube.
必须再来一剂大腿润滑油
Oh, good. Luke.
很好  卢克
Dad, I was with you on the tightrope.
爸爸  走钢丝时我支持你
I was your wing man in the wing-eating competition.
吃鸡翅比赛时  我是你的搭档
But I'm not feeling this one.
但这次我不愿意陪着你
You're missing Christmas Eve.
你要错过平安夜了
There's something more important than Christmas, son
有些东西比圣诞节更重要  儿子
-- pride.
那就是自尊
If I don't make it to Canada,
如果我到不了加拿大
your mom wins, and this baby
你妈妈获胜了  这宝贝
ends up in the garage first thing in the morning.
明天一早就会被丢进车库里
Our garage?
我们家车库吗
I'm in charge of the recycling.
我负责回收垃圾
I'm supposed to bring it from the garage to the curb
我该在周四早晨六点从车库
by 6:00 A.M. Thursday morning.
拿出垃圾放在马路边
I may have missed a few weeks.
我也许错过了几周
Shoot!
该死
Maybe more than a few weeks.
也许不止几周
After a while, the pile just got so big,
过了一阵子  垃圾堆越来越大
I couldn't bring it out the night before
我不能在前一晚把垃圾都搬出去
or people would ask questions.
不然人们会问问题的
I don't need people asking questions.
我可不需要人们问问题
Then you're right! You've got to finish!
你说得对  你得完成
You'll never use this thing in the garage! It's too drafty!
你在车库里可用不上这个  那里风太大
That's why I'm going to Canada, buddy --
所以我才要去加拿大啊  儿子
to avoid the draft!
躲开大风
No.
不行
Bang.
找到了
I know we've been hiking for an hour, but...
我知道我们已经走了一小时了  但是
worth it when you look at this beauty, huh?
这棵树多美啊  真是太值得了  对吧
That's why you don't cut down the first tree you see.
所以不要砍伐你看到的第一棵树
This is literally the first tree we saw.
这就是我们看到的第一棵树
There's our car.
我们的车就停在那里
No, we started that way.
不  我们是从那边开始的
So, you're arguing
所以你的意思是
that we walked entirely around the earth?
我们围着地球绕了一圈吗
Give me the ax.
把斧子给我
Don't give me that look.
别那样看着我
Trees are like women.
树就像女人一样
The best ones make you work a little bit harder.
你得多费功夫  才能得到最好的
She's just not that into you.
她只是没那么喜欢你
- I know! - Sorry it too long!
-就是啊  -抱歉花了这么长时间
Oh, it's fine.
没事啦
Claire and I were having a nice time catching up.
克莱尔和我聊得很开心
I am really sorry that I am late.
真抱歉我迟到了
No, you're not.
你才不抱歉
No, I'm not.
的确如此
Mm-hmm. It's fine.
没关系啦
Just hope I didn't talk Pilar's ear off!
希望我这个话唠没烦到皮娜
No!
没有啦
I love hearing about your family
我喜欢听你聊你的家人
and your big, new job!
和你重大新工作的事
Oh, well, it's -- it's not such a big job.
这工作不算重大啦
I mean, I'm really just working for my dad.
我只是在为我老爸工作而已
But you're working hard.
但你有努力工作啊
I'm proud of you.
我为你感到骄傲
- How do they look? - Ooh! Perfect!
-看起来怎么样  -完美
- Yes. - You are a wonderful student.
-太棒了  -你是超棒的学生
-Thank you.  -My grandmother taught my mother.
-谢谢  -这是我祖母教给我妈妈的
My mother taught me.
我妈妈又教给了我
And now, I teach Claire.
现在我教给了克莱尔
And don't be so modest.
别谦虚啦
I respect a woman who can raise a family
我尊重那种能养育家庭
and have a full-time job.
同时又有全职工作的女人
Can you believe that on Fridays,
你能相信吗  在周五
they don't even have to dress up?
她们都没必要盛装打扮
Taste. Taste. Taste.
尝尝  尝尝
Sometimes, they even wear sweatpants.
有时她们甚至穿运动裤哦
Would you like to lick the batter?
你想舔一舔面糊吗
Yes! Oh, yes!
超想
- Me, too! - No, no, no!
-我也想  -不行
Helpers only.
帮忙的人才能吃到
I don't make the rules.
规矩不是我定的
Oh, Lily, what a beautiful ornament!
莉莉  装饰品真漂亮
That's gonna make a little kid very happy.
这会让一个小朋友很开心的
Wait. I don't get to keep this?
等等  我不能留着吗
Why am I killing myself?
为什么我还做得这么费力
Okay, kids!
好了  孩子们
We've got a visitor from the North Pole,
北极有人来探望我们了
and he brought presents!
而且他带了礼物哦
Hey! Hey. How's it going?
喂  怎么样
There are no Puppy Pounds anywhere.
到处都买不到胖胖狗之家
It's like trying to find a Cabbage Patch Kid
简直就像在1983年的平安夜寻找
on Christmas Eve 1983.
椰菜娃娃一样
Still hurts, huh?
还无法释怀呐
I had her bed all made.
我把她的床都铺好了
Okay. Well, Lily is gonna be devastated.
好吧  莉莉会难过死的
Call around. Get us on some lists.
打电话问问  把我们排上预订名单
You have to do something!
你得做些什么
I'll figure it out.
我会想办法的
How's the fundraiser?
募捐会怎么样
Oh, well, I'm managing, you know.
我在设法对付
Oh, bring the checkbook.
把支票本拿来
You can always tell when they're gearing up for the big ask --
能看出他们准备提出重大请求的样子
Fill you full of freebies.
给了很多免费赠品
Oh, hey, I gotta go. Got to help somebody.
我得挂了  得去帮帮别人
Hi! Classic.
你好  经典小丑
Flawlessly executed.
扔得真完美
If I had one...
如果我有一个...
Just trying to bring a smile to you folks.
只想让你们能笑逐颜开
- You're gonna get through this. - Get through what?
-你会度过这一切的  -度过什么
Don't be embarrassed.
别不好意思
Everyone here is in the same boat.
我们都处境相同
We are?
是吗
Best thing about the hot chocolate --
热可可最妙的一点
they let us keep the mug.
喝完后杯子也归我们
I thought it was a charity event for the needy.
我以为这是为有需要的人募捐的慈善活动
Turns out, it was a charity event for the needy!
结果是让有需要人士来参加的慈善活动
Look! Santa gave me a puppy pound!
瞧  圣诞老人给了我一个胖胖狗之家
What? No.
什么  不
I'm finally happy!
我终于开心啦
I'd like a picture for the newsletter.
我需要给新闻报道拍张照片
Oh. You can show your mommy.
你可以给你妈妈看看
I don't have a mommy.
我没有妈妈
This is why I do this.
所以我才办这活动
That cramp could be a heart attack.
也许不是抽筋  可能要犯心脏病
Here's some advice I've been holding back on.
我要给你留下一些建议
Always shave with the grain.
刮胡子的时候要顺着皮肤纹理刮
No reputable talent agent
真正有本事的地产中介
will ever ask for money up-front.
是不会一开始就谈钱的
Dad, you're fine.
爸  你没事的
I really want to quit, Luke!
卢克  我好想放弃啊
No, you're gonna make it!
不  你可以的
He was never gonna make it.
他根本不可能做到的
I just needed to buy some time.
我只是要拖延时间
That's a lot of product you're moving.
你要搬的东西真够多的
Just bring it to a recycling place.
带到垃圾回收场就行了
Not until I get paid.
给了钱我才办事
Just so you know, this is six weeks' allowance.
这可是人家六个星期的补贴呢
Oh, you have the coolest parents ever.
你家长真是酷毙了
I want to know when you're about to leave,
我得知道你什么时候出发
so give me a honk.
按一下喇叭通知我
- Honk! -  From your car.
-嘀嘀  -按汽车的喇叭
The best business card is a firm handshake.
最好的名片就是有力的握手
The best pick-up line is a tight pair of dockers.
最好的搭讪诀窍是穿紧身工作裤
The best dockers are --
最好的工作裤是...
Dad, save your breath! You're in the last five miles.
爸爸  别说了  还有最后五英里了
- I'm never gonna make it! - Of course you are!
-我永远也跑不完了  -你当然能
Then again, do what you want. I got stuff to do.
不过你爱怎么办怎么办吧  我还有事
- I'm gonna quit. - Cool.
-我要放弃了  -好吧
What's one more failure?
再失败一次又怎么样呢
You ever wonder why we take such a crazy route to school?
你想过我们为什么要绕远去学校吗
So I don't have to drive by certain places --
因为那样我就不用路过某些地方了
The flute teacher's house I went to once...
那个我只去过一次的长笛老师家
The French cooking academy I quit after learning
那个我只学了五大基本酱料中的两种
only two of the five mother sauces...
就退出了的法餐烹饪学校
The hot yoga studio I left after "Happy baby."
那个只学了一个动作就放弃了的瑜伽教室
I guess there's no avoiding
看来是怎么也躲不过
this big failure sitting in my garage.
车库里这个巨大的失败了
Get up.
起来
I appreciate it, buddy, but --
谢谢你  伙计  不过...
I don't know anything about flutes
我不会你说的长笛
or cooking or happy babies...
或者烹饪或者瑜伽...
But I'm damn sure getting my dad to Canada.
但我拼了老命也要让你去加拿大
Now, mount that beast.
加油跑到终点吧
Thank you, son.
谢谢你  儿子
You can thank me after you cross the finish line
等你跑过终点开始庆祝的时候
and the celebration begins.
再谢我
Just picture that.
想象一下吧
I'm picturing it!
我能想象到
I'm really picturing it!
我真的能想象到
Thanks, Santa.
谢谢你  圣诞老人
Yeah. You got it.
好  没事
Don't forget a candy cane from Mrs. Claus!
别忘了圣诞夫人给你的糖果棒
Oh! I got to take a break.
我得休息会儿
- What? - What? What?
-什么  -搞什么
Um...it's okay!
没关系
Does anybody want to take a picture with me?
谁想和我照张相呀
- I'll do it. - Oh, maybe just the kids.
-我想  -我是说孩子们
- What was that? - What was what?
-刚才怎么回事  -什么怎么回事
Santa doesn't take breaks.
圣诞老人不能休息
He visits the North Pole!
他要去北极的
And why do you leave your things all over?
而且你怎么把这里弄得乱七八糟的
Who do you think cleans this place up?
最后是我要打扫这里好吗
Oh, you are such a nag!
你怎么像祥林嫂似的
Can't we at least
我们连在过节的时候
act like a happy couple during the holidays?
假装是幸福的一对都不行吗
For the children!
为了孩子们
Another hot chocolate?
你还喝热巧克力
How many more of those are you going to drink?
你还想喝多少杯啊
At least it's warm, unlike you!
至少它是暖的  不像你
He travels a lot.
圣诞老人常在外出差
She's put on cookie weight.
圣诞夫人吃曲奇吃胖了
It's hard.
日子不好过
Yes, you can put me on
没问题  你可以把我放在
the "Last-minute shoppers" waiting list.
"亡羊补牢礼物购买者"的名单上
- Unbelievable. - Oh! Well, there he is!
-真行  -你也在这里啊
H-hey, Jotham!
乔森
Oh, looks like someone did
看来你也是
a little last-minute Christmas shopping.
临到圣诞才想起要买礼物
That Zaniel's a lucky guy.
那个赞尼尔真是幸运啊
Yes, he is.
他的确很幸运
But these are for Pepper's party.
但这些是要带去胡娇的派对的
His invitation said, "No gifts, please."
他的请柬上不是说了不要带礼物吗
Mm, say that again...
重复一遍那句话
as Pepper.
用胡娇的语气
No gifts?
没带礼物吗
Please.
想不想活了
5 o'clock, Christmas Eve,
现在是平安夜的下午五点
and I have to find a dozen perfect presents
我还得去买最完美的礼物
for the world's snarkiest, cattiest men...
给世界上最挑剔最尖刻的男人们
My dear, dear friends.
我亲爱的朋友们
Pull! Pull! Pull!
拉  拉  再拉
Yeah. Hey, take a break.
好了  休息会儿吧
- This is taking forever. - It's supposed to.
-这也太费时了  -本来就是
Took my dad and I all day to get a tree.
原来我和我爸要花一整天弄倒一棵树
And when he finally brought her down,
当终于把树砍下来的时候
he used to celebrate with a cigar.
他会抽根雪茄来庆祝
I was just a kid, so I'd have a cigarette.
我那时还是个孩子  所以就抽根香烟
All right. Grab the other end.
好了  抓住另一边
There we go.
这就对了
Now we got a groove.
这就进入状态了吧
Yeah. There we --
好了  这就可以...
It won't budge!
它就是不断
The hell is this wood made of?
这木头是他妈什么做的啊
They ought to make saws out of it!
都能拿来做锯了好吗
Let's face it. The tree's beaten us.
面对现实吧  这棵树把我们打败了
Hey, we're Pritchetts. We don't quit.
我们普里契特家的人是不会半途而废的
Besides, all my tools are stuck in it.
再说了  我的工具都卡在里面
I got it.
我知道该怎么办了
It's simple physics.
非常简单的原理
A little pressure,
给这棵树施点压
the thing will snap where we put the blade in.
它就会在我们砍的地方断掉
- Done. - Just hit the gas.
-这不就完事了  -赶紧的吧
It's working.
凑效了吧
That's why they call it yankee engine--
这才叫北方汉子做的发动机
Get down!
小心
It's bald on one side now!
半棵树都秃了
It'll be fine!
没事的
We'll just comb over some branches!
两边匀一匀就好了
Oh, Claire, I thought that you had left.
克莱尔  我以为你走了呢
She was going to,
她本来是要走了
But I wanted to show her how much better she looks
但我想让她看看没有这些头发挡着
without this hair blocking her pretty face.
她的脸  她有多美丽动人
She does have beautiful hair, though.
她头发确实很美
I see.
我知道
What did she say?
她说什么
That you picked a good color...
说你碰巧赶上一个好发色
At least, I think that's what she said
反正我觉得她是这个意思
with that American accent.
她美国口音太重
You don't have to entertain her.
你不用哄她高兴
After all, she's my mother.
毕竟她是我妈
Ah, these used to be Glorita's favorite!
这是歌洛莉亚以前最爱吃的
She used to do headstands to get extra cookies.
她以前为了能多吃点常做手头倒立
At least, she'd try.
至少会努力去做
Yeah, but it's not easy!
是的  真的不容易做到
I mean, it's hard enough to keep all this right-side up!
我站着的时候要保持她们坚挺都很不容易
Imagine when I had to put it all right-side down!
你可以想象倒过来会有多难
- It was... - Oh, my gosh.
-那太...  -天呐
I can't believe I can still do it!
真不敢相信我还能做到
Look at that.
看呐
Oh, wow. Look at Claire, Gloria!
看看克莱尔  歌洛莉亚
Very good! Two cookies for you!
真棒  给你两块小点心
Thank you!
谢谢
Uh, yeah, but she needs a pedicure.
是啊  可她需要修修脚
Look at that.
看呐
You knocked me down!
你把我弄倒了
- I did not. - Yes, you did, too!
-我没有  -有  你弄的
Girls! Girls! Girls! No need to fight.
姑娘们  姑娘们  别吵了
I don't have a favorite.
我没有偏爱你们哪一个
Why the hell not?!
为什么没有
I am very disappointed in both of you.
我对你们两个非常失望
Family members should treat each other
家庭成员应该用爱和尊重
with love and respect.
来对待彼此
Except that Claire is not part of our family.
但克莱尔不是我们家的人
- Cierra la boca! - No. No, no.
-闭嘴  -不不
She's right-- unless that's what you just said.
她说的对  除非你刚才说的就是这个
I can't tell, 'cause I-I only took French,
我听不懂  因为我只学了法语
And je parle un peu.
能讲一点点
Oh, you have a beautiful accent.
你的语调很美啊
Really? Do you think so?
真的吗  你这么觉得吗
- Ay-ya! Por favor? - I'm sorry. I...
-拜托  -抱歉 我
I-I'm jealous.
我很嫉妒
Ay, Claire.
克莱尔
But you're beautiful, too, in your own way.
你也很美  个性的美
No. I'm not jealous of you.
不  我不是嫉妒你
I am jealous of how your mother
我嫉妒你妈妈
comes all the way to see you from Colombia,
大老远从哥伦比亚来看你
When my own mother won't even get on a bus
可我妈甚至都不愿意从她住的
from the Almond co-op she lives on three hours away.
阿尔蒙公寓坐车过来  只有三小时路程
She sends presents, no?
她会寄礼物来的  没有吗
Yeah. It's the same thing every year.
有寄  但每年都一样
It's always slippers.
永远是拖鞋
I am sorry.
我为你感到难过
Thank you.
谢谢
But I shouldn't take it out on you
但我不该因为我妈妈不好
just 'cause I have a lousy mom.
就把气撒在你头上
Don't disrespect your mother!
不许不尊重你妈妈
- Is she always like this? - Yes.
-她总这样吗  -是的
Did you-- did you ever think maybe there's a reason
你就没想过也许她寄给你那样礼物
she sends you that gift?
是有原因的吗
Yeah, 'cause she found something
想过  因为在我8岁时
when I was 8 years old that I actually liked,
她发现了我很喜欢的礼物
and she hasn't thought about it since.
从此就再也没花心思选礼物给我
Well, maybe she thinks about it a lot.
也许她花了很多心思
Maybe she remembers a time when she made you happy,
也许她记得她让你开心的那个时刻
and she wants to go back there.
她想回到过去
Well, now I feel terrible.
现在我好难受
The only thing I sent her was an e-card.
我只寄给她一张电子贺卡
We don't like to admit it...
我们都不愿意承认
But mothers never get over
可妈妈们永远不会忘记
the day their daughters leave them.
女儿们离开她们的那天
We never stop needing our little girls.
我们从未停止对自己的女儿的依赖
I will never stop needing you, mama.
我也从未停止对你的依赖  妈妈
Excuse me.
不好意思
Excuse me, elf,
不好意思  精灵
it's been 45 minutes.
已经过去45分钟了
Where's Santa?
圣诞老人去哪了
I don't know!
我不知道
Maybe he's a little busy making presents
他可能忙着为世界上所有的孩子
for every child in the world.
做礼物呢
One second!
等一下
Where is he?
他人呢
He said he was going out for a pack of candy canes.
他说他要出去买一包糖果棒
You mean like those?
你是指那玩意吗
Okay. Wake up! He is not coming back!
好了  醒醒  他不会回来了
We need to change into our regular clothes
我们需要换回便装
and sneak out.
溜出去
Who am I kidding?
我想什么呢
My eyes are unforgettable.
我的双眼是让人过目难忘的
I couldn't even hold on to a fake husband.
我连个假丈夫都留不住
I always thought you were the tough one to live with,
我总认为你是难相处的人
but maybe I am.
可或许我才是
Okay, they've breached the jelly bean moat. This is a problem.
他们已经冲破了糖果围栏  问题大了
It's a big problem. All this time, I've been waiting
这是个大问题  我一直在等一个
for a guy to see the true me,
能了解我的人
and now I'm scared he will.
可现在我却害怕被他看透
Oh, my god! They've got Blitzen!
天呐  他们打倒布利岑了
What's going to happen to me?
我会怎么样
Am I just going to nitpick everyone until they leave me?
我会一直挑剔别人直到人家离开我吗
- Hey, mom found somebody! - That's true.
-妈妈都找到对象了  -这倒是
Okay, listen.
好了  听着
We really need to get out of here.
我们真的得离开这里
But I just want to let you know
我只想让你知道
that you weren't all bad to live with. I thought--
你不是那么难相处 我觉得
Oh, my god!
天呐
Where's santa?!
圣诞老人呢
Only 100 more yards.
只剩下一百码了
You're just about there!
你就要到达了
Can you see it?
看到了吗
It's so beautiful. It's so green.
未来真美好  满眼绿色
And, wow, those are high up there.
而且  好高啊
The mountains?
山脉吗
No, my shorts again.
不是  还是我的短裤
Would you mind giving them one last tug?
介意最后再拉它一下吗
You're crossing the border.
你穿过边境了[越界]
Yeah, I know, and I feel bad asking,
我知道  我也不好意思问出口
But I'm tasting cotton.
可我感觉到它紧紧地包着我
No! You did it! You're in Canada!
不是  你做到了  你到加拿大了
Wait. What?
等等  什么
I did it? I did it!
我做到了  我做到了
Let's go tell mom!
我们快去告诉妈妈
Wait.
等等
How did I used to walk?
我以前是怎么走路的
All right. Come on, sweetie.
好了  宝贝儿  快来
Let's go.
我们走
Uh, we're serving Christmas dinner.
我们提供圣诞晚餐
Uh, no. That's fine.
不  没关系
We have to actually get going, so...
我们必须得走了
But I haven't eaten today.
可我今天还没吃过东西呢
Oh, you poor thing!
可怜的小家伙
No, she's fine. She's fine.
她没关系的  没事
Oh, there he is.
他来了
Honey, where did you get this coat?
亲爱的  你这外套在哪拿的
Sorry, kids.
不好意思  孩子们
It looks like we've run out of coats and toys.
外套和玩具好像发完了
That's okay, mom. At least I got to see presents.
没关系  妈妈  至少我看到礼物了
Okay. Come on. Let's go.
好了  快过来  我们走
Hey! How are my do-gooders?
我的好心人们今天过得怎么样
Did you have fun?
玩得开心吗
Yep. Talk about it in the car. Oh, my gosh.
还行  上车再说 我的天啊
What are these?
这些是什么
Yeah, I went a little crazy, huh?
是啊  我是不是有点太疯狂了
No! No, no! It's a Christmas miracle!
不  不  这是个圣诞节奇迹
Kids! Kids! Who wants presents?
孩子们  孩子们  谁想要礼物
Cam, what are you doing?
小卡  你在做什么
No, trust me. Lily has enough.
不  相信我  莉莉的礼物足够了
- Cam, Cam. - Everybody, Merry Christmas!
-小卡  小卡  -大家圣诞快乐
Oh! Not that one.
那个不可以
Feliz navidad!
圣诞快乐
Okay, but those aren't for Lily.
好吧  可是那些不是给莉莉的
"His-and-his shower clogs?"
"他与他的沐浴拖鞋"
They're for Pepper's party.
这些是要带去胡娇的派对的
He said, "No gifts, please."
他说过不用带礼物的
Imagine how Pepper would say that.
想象一下胡娇说那句话的语气
What's a Himalayan salt plate?
"喜马拉雅盐盘"是什么东西
You can season your food while you serve it. Yeah.
你可以一边上菜一边调味
Body-fat scale?
脂肪秤
I wish I would've had one of those when I was your age.
我像你这么大的时候很想要一个
- You're welcome. - Who's Robert Mapplethorp?
[美国八十年代黑白片摄影大师]
Actually, I'm gonna need that one back. Sorry.
实际上  我得把那个拿回来 不好意思
That's okay.
没关系
All I really wanted this year was a Puppy Pound.
我今年真正想要的就是一个胖胖狗之家
Here. You can have mine.
给  我的可以给你
It's really fun.
可好玩了
Oh, my gosh.
我的天啊
That's the sweetest thing I've ever seen!
这是我见到过最感人的事了
Lily, honey, that was so nice!
莉莉  宝贝儿  你这样做太好了
It's okay. I'll get one tomorrow.
没事儿  我明天还会有一个
Um, well, you know what? About that --
那个  你知道吗  关于那个
Cam? Cam?
小卡  小卡
Uh, that was a t-o-y s-t-o-r-e.
是玩具店打来的
- What? - Someone returned their Puppy Pound.
-怎么了  -有人退了一个胖胖狗之家
W-we can't get over there in time before the store closes!
可我们在他们关门之前赶不过去
Wait, you know who lives right over there?
等等  你知道谁就住那家店旁边吗
Oh, no. No!
不  不
Almost there.
马上就到
No.
不
No! Why?!
不  为什么会这样
Why-y-y-y-y?!
为什么
In hindsight, the cigar was a mistake.
事后诸葛亮一下  那支烟是个错误
So, what do we do now?
那我们现在怎么办
We go home.
我们回家吧
I thought Pritchetts never give up.
我以为普里契特家的人是不会放弃的
They know when to give up,
他们知道什么时候应该放手
which is its own kind of victory.
也算是某种战胜自我
- Unless... - what?
-除非  -怎么了
No it's crazy.
算了  太疯狂了
Unless...
除非
Are you really gonna make me ask you again?
你真的想我再问一遍吗
...we somehow apply pressure to the axhead already in the tree.
我们可以想办法给树干上的斧头施加压力
I bet we can use the jack from the car.
可以用车上的千斤顶
Of course. The upward motion will split the trunk. Yeah.
不错  向上的力可以撕裂树干
We can always tell people that's how we did it.
我们可以跟别人说我们是那么做的
That is how we did it.
我们就是那么做到的
People love getting new things...
人们总喜欢得到新东西
But the best stuff has a story behind it.
不过最好的东西背后都有个故事
Damn fine tree.
超棒的树
Except the saw's still stuck in the truck.
只是锯子还卡在树上
Yeah, you're gonna want to keep your brother away from that, huh?
你要负责不让你弟弟靠近那个
A lot of times, it's only after we get rid of something...
很多时候  只有当我们失去了之后
Room for me?
有我的位置吗
...that we realize how much we miss it.
才意识到自己有多怀念
Oh! Nice!
真好
Good job, Luke!
干得不错  卢克
Yay! A Puppy Pound!
好棒  胖胖狗之家
And things that seem worthless
看起来没什么价值的东西
suddenly turn out to be super valuable...
突然就变得很有价值
Okay, everybody, picture in front of the tree.
大家一起到圣诞树前合影
Timer's set. Ready?
定好时间了  准备好了吗
What? No!
什么  不
...maybe even precious...
甚至是宝贵
Which is why I thought getting rid of this stuff
所以我才觉得我们也许
would be a huge mistake.
不应该把这些丢掉
Nice try.
得了吧
You still owe us six weeks' allowance,
你欠我们六个星期的补贴
and the fireworks.
还有烟花
How could you screw this up?
你居然把事情搞砸了
What?
你说什么
I'll see you in Vancouver, eh?
我们温哥华见
No. Luke, do the accent again?
不对  卢克  再学一遍口音
Oh, are you on that machine?
你还在跑着呢
Yes, Juliana, but unlike your husband,
对  朱莉安娜  但跟你老公不同的是
I'll be finished before you know it.
我会在你反应过来之前就完事的
You know what? It's actually easier this way!
你知道吗  这样其实更轻松了
Wonder if you could patent a movement?
不知道能不能给这个动作申请专利
Call it "Fliptical" --
就叫"菲式旋转"
Dad, trick or treaters!
爸  小朋友们来要糖果了
We're out of candy!
我们的糖发完了
Who is this dad?
这个爸爸是谁
I'm Gandalf.
我是甘道夫
Who's on?
我来啦